欢迎回来，现在是浓缩物课程的第14讲或
welcome back it's now the 14th lecture
of the condensed matter course more or
少一点，我们结束谈论散射时，有一些
less we finished talking about
scattering there's a couple of little
零散的点点滴，我打算稍后再尝试
bits and pieces of scattering that I'm
going to try to pick up later maybe at
在其他一些讲座的结尾，我想继续讲下去，并使用我们所拥有的
the end of some other lectures instead
I'd like to move on and use what we've
当我们研究散射以便回头研究其他类型时学到的
learned when we studied scattering in
order to go back and study other types
晶体中的波浪类型我们最初感兴趣的波浪类型是
of waves in crystals the type of waves
we were interested in originally we're
电子波，振动波或声子，让我提醒您一些
electron waves and vibrational waves or
phonons so let me remind you a few
我们已经了解了一维关于电子波的东西，然后
things we had learned about electron
waves in one dimension and then we're
将尝试从我们所学到的知识中推广到更高的维度
gonna try to generalize up to higher
dimensions from what we've learned so
让我们回想一下电子的紧密结合模型
let's a recall the tight binding model
tight binding model for electrons
一维一维绑定模型，我们将考虑两个轨道的情况
binding model in 1d in 1d and we're
gonna consider the case of two orbitals
每个单位晶胞有两个轨道，或者如果每个单位晶胞有两个，则可以是两个
with two orbitals per unit cell or if
it's per unit cell and that can be two
原子在每个原子中一个轨道，也可以是同一原子上的两个轨道
atoms one orbital in each atom or it
could be two orbitals on the same atom
每个晶胞一个原子，我们可以绘制缩小区域中的色散
one atom per unit cell and we can we can
draw up the dispersion in reduced zone
方案这里是K这里是能量这里是PI超过这里的负PI超过了
scheme here's K here's energy here's PI
over a here's minus PI over a that's the
Brauns拥有自己的BZ Ron区，我们可以这样写得出分散类型
Brauns own BZ Ron zone we can write draw
the dispersion kind of like this and
像在布劳恩斯自己的每个波矢K上的两种模式一样，否则我们可以展开
like this two modes at each wave vector
K in the Brauns own or we can unfold
扩展区域方案中的图片看起来像这样
that picture in the extended zone scheme
looking like this
这是K，这里是PI，而这里是负PI，而在a和两个PI
here's K here's PI over a here's minus
PI over a there's two PI over a and
这是一个负两个pi，因此第一个模式的图片相同
here's minus two pi over a so we have
the same picture for the first mode and
然后在第二种模式下，我们将把东西移到
then for the second mode we're going to
shift things over shift the thing on the
在两个PI上向左或向右移动两个PI，使其看起来像这样，然后将
left or to the right by two PI over a to
make it look like this and ship the
在右边的两个PI上方的一块上，使其看起来像这样
piece on the right over by two PI over a
to the left to make it look like this
所以我们这里有所谓的第一个青铜拥有者
so we have what we called the first
bronze own here first bronze own BZ here
然后这些是我们的第二块青铜，第二块青铜
and then these pieces here we're the
second bronze own second bronze own BZ
所以有用的是K等于零
and so it's useful
there's K equals zero all right in the
中间，尝试将这个概念推广到三个维度是很有用的，或者
middle it's useful to try to generalize
this concept to three dimensions or
较大的尺寸，所以我们呃，一般来说，
higher dimensions so let's uh let's do
that so generally the Bruins zone for
一个区域，因为我们正在考虑三维中的电子
one zone since we're thinking about
electrons in three dimensions is going
总是定义为倒数空间中的晶胞，我们将拥有
to be always defined as the unit cell in
reciprocal space and we're going to have
弄清楚我们的意思是第一个青铜拥有第二个青铜拥有，等等
to figure out what we mean by first
bronze own second bronze own and so
因此，这是我们定义的将军和青铜器将军
forth so it's a general and bronze own
general general nth bronze own we define
如下，所以我们将从k空间中的第一个青铜点开始
as follows so we'll start with the first
bronze own points in k-space
越接近越接近越接近K等于零K
that are closer to that are closer to
that are closer to K equals zero K
等于零，然后等于任何其他值
equals zero then to any other any other
倒数晶格点静止点R第一个青铜器是
reciprocal lattice point resit lat
point R the first bronze own are the
第一个青铜拥有第一个BZ，所以第一个青铜拥有的所有这些点都是
first bronze own first BZ so all these
points in the first bronze own are
靠近K点等于零然后靠近另一个倒易晶格
closer to the point at K equals zero
then to the other reciprocal lattice
点在这里是一个倒数晶格点，在这里的2减去2 pi
points here's a reciprocal lattice point
here at two minus two pi over a here's
另一个互易晶格点在此处位于两个pi之上
another reciprocal lattice point here at
two pi over a and everything between
减去a的PI和a的PI构成第一个青铜
minus PI over a and PI over a
constitutes the first bronze own
它比其他倒数晶格点更接近K等于零
it's closer to K equals zero than it is
to any other reciprocal lattice point
您可能对这个定义有点陌生，因为实际上
this definition might look a little
familiar to you because in fact it's the
与大nur位点单元格的定义相同，因此等于Vig护士位点单元格
same definition as the big nur site cell
so this equals the Vig nurse site cell
在倒数晶格中，K的Seitz单元等于零，K的零点等于零
Seitz cell of the K equals zero point of
K equals zero in reciprocal lattice in
倒数格子听起来是否很熟悉，我希望所有观点
reciprocal lattice does that sound
familiar I hope all points they're
更接近给定的倒易晶格点，然后接近所有
closer to a given reciprocal lattice
point then to any all points that are
相比给定的晶格点更接近给定的晶格点
closer to a given lattice point than to
any other lattice point constitute its
Vigna站点像元，因此所有比K更近的点等于零
Vigna site cell so all points that are
closer to K equals zero than to any
其他倒易晶格点构成了
other reciprocal lattice point
constitute the bigger sites cell of the
K等于倒数空间中的零点是是好的怎么样
K equals zero point in reciprocal space
good yes okay good so how about the
第二个青铜拥有的点，其中K等于零是第二个最接近的点是第二个
second bronze own points where K equals
zero is the second closest is the second
最接近的里斯（如果该点是第二个青铜器，则是第二个）
closest Reese if that point that point
are the second bronze own are the second
第二个是Z，例如，如果我们在此处选择一个点X，则将此点称为x
second be Z so for example if we pick
pick a point here X call this point x
与此点X最接近的第一个倒数晶格点是第二个
the first closest reciprocal lattice
point to this point X is here the second
最接近点X的倒数晶格点K为零，因此
closest reciprocal lattice point to the
point X is K equals zero therefore this
X点在第二个熊身上很好，这就是定义，所以
point X is in the second Bruins own good
okay that's the definition so a couple
关于这些定义的注释首先是青铜自己的边界二
of notes about these definitions first
of all one bronze own boundary two
相对的两个相对的相对的Z边界是倒数晶格向量
opposite two opposite opposite be Z
boundary is a reciprocal lattice vector
是他们up了一口的补给向量，让我们看看，所以这是一个青铜色的
is a resupply vector they sip lad
back let's see so here's a bronze own
边界是第二个青铜器上的第一个青铜器之间的边界-
boundary it's the boundary between the
first bronze on the second bronze own -
在这是另一个PI上，PI是减去PI上调加PI的相反值
PI over a here's another one it's the
opposite one from minus PI raise plus PI
R在它们之间的距离是两个PI，实际上是一个倒数晶格
R a distance between them is two PI over
a which is indeed a reciprocal lattice
向量类似，这是第二个青铜拥有者和外出者之间的边界
vector similarly here's a boundary
between the second bronze own and out
这里实际上是第三个青铜器，所以这是青铜器的边界
here actually would be the third bronze
own and so it's a bronze own boundary
从那里到相对的青铜本国边界的距离
the distance from it to the opposite
bronze own boundary over here at plus
在a上的两个PI是在a上的四个PI，这也是一个倒数晶格矢量，
two PI over a is four PI over a and that
is also a reciprocal lattice vector that
通常是一个真实的声明，好吧，有一个类似的例子
is generally a true statement okay
there's a similar so one a sort of Kavya
一个必然的结论是BZ边界或者也许不是
a corollary of this is that BZ
boundaries or maybe a maybe it's not
推论，但这些边界几乎是等价的陈述
corollary but it's almost equivalent
statement these e boundaries are points
其中K的绝对值等于某个G的K的绝对值加G的绝对值
where absolute value of K equals
absolute value of K plus G for some G
对于一些倒数晶格向量G好的，例如，您需要
for some reciprocal lattice vector G
okay so for example you need you need to
让K和K加G让我们看看K和k k + g的大小相同
have K and K plus G let's see it was K
and k k+ g having the same magnitude for
g的小猫是一些倒数晶格向量，所以如果减去pi
kitten for g being some reciprocal
lattice vector so if you take minus pi
在a上，您在8008上添加了倒数晶格矢量2pi，得到的是PI
over a you add a reciprocal lattice
vector 2pi over 8008 you get plus PI
那些具有相同的幅度，因此您处于柏林区域边界
over a those have the same magnitude so
you're on the Berlin zone boundary
类似地，您将负2 PI减去a，然后向其添加一个倒数晶格矢量4
similarly you take minus 2 PI over a you
add a reciprocal lattice vector to it 4
您的PI等于2，加上2的PI的幅度相同，因此您的
PI over a you get 2 plus 2 PI over a
that has the same magnitude so your
荣誉棕色区域边界第二个对棕色很重要的声明
honor brown zone boundary the second
statement which is important about brown
区域是每个BZ*区域在三个区域中具有相同的面积或体积
zones is each BZ bran zone has the same
the same area or volume in three
尺寸相同的区域并代表
dimensions same area and and represents
代表每个K点每个晶体动量每个晶体波矢量I
represents each K point each crystal
momentum each crystal wave vector I
猜测波向量K曾经是构造青铜的总体思路
guess wave vector K once that was a
general idea of constructing the bronze
首先，它代表了每个物理上不同的波
own in the first place that every
physically different wave is represented
正好在青铜器中拥有一次，第二个青铜器拥有相当于
exactly once in the bronze own the
second bronze own is equivalent to the
第一个青铜器，我们只是将棋子以两种不同的方式移动
first bronze own we've just sort of
moved the pieces around in two different
放置，但每个波向量K在每个波向量内恰好代表一次
places but each wave vector K is
representing exactly once inside each
顺便说一句，从第二个青铜器本身可以明显看出您
bronze own incidentally is it obvious
from the second bronze own that you
可以定义第三个青铜像点，其中K等于
would define the third bronze own
analogously points where the K equals
零是第三最接近的倒数晶格点将是第三青铜
zero is the third closest reciprocal
lattice point would be the third bronze
是的，所以第一，第二，三等分可以拥有任意数量的青铜器
own so yeah the first second third you
can have as many bronze owns as you want
最后的最后声明很有用，我认为这是一项功课
the final the final statement which is
useful I think this is a homework
第三个作业的作业设置为K个州数K个州
assignment on the third homework set
that the number of K States number of K
在每个BZ中我们甚至在演讲中证明的状态BZ等于单位数
States we even proved this in lecture in
each B Z BZ equals the number of unit
听起来很熟悉，我们证明了这一点
cells unit cells in system in system
does that sound familiar we proved this
在一个方面，我认为对于功课，您应该在三个方面进行证明
in one dimension I think for homework
you're supposed to prove it in three
尺寸，这通常也是真实的陈述，因此实际上让我
dimensions it is also generally a true
statement so actually let me do an
二维的示例，以使其更清晰，因此我们将
example of this in two dimensions to
make this more clear so this we're gonna
从真实空间中的正方形晶格开始正方形的倒数晶格
start with a square lattice in real
space the reciprocal lattice of a square
格子也是正方形格子，所以我画了一个正方形，它应该是
lattice is also a square lattice so I've
drawn a square last it's supposed to be
作为倒数格子，所以又是方形格子
as the reciprocal lattice so it's a
square lattice again I've colored some
点的不同只是为了使他们易于谈论K点
of the points differently just to make
them easy to talk about the point at K
等于零，我在中间涂了黑色，所以首先我们要尝试
equals zero I've colored black in the
center and so first we're going to try
建造第一个青铜人，就是这种黑色的维尼亚·塞兹（Vigna Seitz）牢房
to construct the first bronze own that
is the Vigna Seitz cell of this black
指向中心，那么如何构造放置的手指Seitz细胞
point in the center so how do you
construct the finger Seitz cell you put
垂直平分线向下到最近的垂直平分线点
down perpendicular bisectors to the
nearest points perpendicular bisectors
到这里的红点，我们将这一点设为垂直平分线
to the red points here we'll make this
point that's a perpendicular bisector
在这里，这个平面这个垂直平分线这两个
here then this this plane this
perpendicular bisector these two also
将所有垂直平分线赋予红点和新点
giving all the perpendicular
bisectors to the red points and the new
该区域的颜色是第一个自己拥有的青铜色，现在的距离
color in the area that is the first
bronze own okay now the distance across
第一个青铜器本身是两个pi，这是一个倒数晶格向量
the first bronze own is two pi over a
which is a reciprocal lattice vector the
方式应该是它们与垂直等分线的距离，
way it's supposed to be that distance
they are from perpendicular bisector and
垂直平分线是倒数晶格矢量，现在让我们寻找
perpendicular bisector is a reciprocal
lattice vector now let's look for the
自己拥有第二座青铜器，我们如何做到这一点，这是一套非常相似的结构
second bronze own how do we do that it's
a set very similar construction you just
开始放下更多垂直平分线，所以这里是第二个平分线
start putting down more perpendicular
bisectors so here the second closest
点集是这些蓝色点，所以我们放下垂直
sets of points are these blue points
here so let's put down perpendicular
像这样的人平分秋色这样的，所以这些是
bisectors to those like this like this
like this like this so these are the
垂直于蓝色的等分线，在这里我们将为
perpendicular bisectors to the blue
points out here we'll color in the
围墙蓝色区域，这是现在拥有的第二个青铜器，让我们检查一下
walled off area blue and this is now the
second bronze own now let's just check
如果您在第二个青铜像这里这样选择一个点，它就符合定义
that it fits the definition if you pick
a point like here in the second bronze
拥有第一个最接近的倒数晶格点是这里的红色点
own the first closest reciprocal lattice
point is this red point here the second
最接近的倒数晶格点为K等于0，因此此处为该点
closest reciprocal lattice point is K
equals 0 therefore this point here
这个蓝色区域中的某个地方是第二个青铜器，现在可以了
somewhere in this blue region is in the
second bronze own good okay now it may
显然，青铜器自身与男爵自身边界之间的距离
not be obvious that the distance across
the bronze own from barons own boundary
到柏林区域边界这是一个互易的晶格矢量，但我将展示
to Berlin zone boundary here is a
reciprocal lattice vector but I'll show
你是这是一个从0到蓝点的倒数晶格向量
you that it is this is a reciprocal
lattice vector from 0 to the blue point
如果你只是这样移动的话，那的确是与娇兰的距离
if you just shift it like that it's
indeed the distance across from Guerlain
区域边界到*区域边界，因此我们可以继续寻找
zone boundary to bran zone boundary so
we can keep going on looking for the
第三*区和建造第三*区，我们必须采取
third bran zone and to construct the
third bran zone we have to take put
垂直于这些绿点的等分线，所以我们要做的是
perpendicular bisectors to these green
points so let's do that put down those
垂直于等分线的绿线，我们
green lines which are perpendicular
bisectors to the green points and we
现在将区域填写为绿色，然后检查其是否满足定义要求
fill in the area now green and let's
check that it satisfies the definition
如果您在绿色区域中选择一个点，则倒数第二个倒数
if you pick a point here in the green
area the first closest reciprocal
晶格点是这个红色点，第二个第二点是蓝色点
lattice point is this red point here the
second closest is the blue point out
在这里，第三个最接近的是K等于中心的0点，所以它在
here the third closest is the K equals 0
point in the center so this is in the
现在，第三个*区域也是从*区域边界到*区域的距离
third bran zone now also the distance
from bran zone boundary to bran zone
整个系统的边界是a的4 pi，这也是一个倒易的晶格
boundary across the system is 4 pi over
a which is also a reciprocal lattice
向量现在，这些定义向您保证的另一件事是
vector now another thing that you've
been promised from these definitions is
每个*区域都有面积，就像那种威力和
that each bran zone has
area looks like the kind of might and
他们每个应该代表每个K点一次，所以青铜拥有
that they should each represent each K
point once so the bronze owns represent
每个可能的K点只有一次，看到我们要做的是
every possible K point exactly
once to see this what we're gonna do is
我们将用一些非常粗糙的方法来解决这个难题
we're going to take the pieces of this
puzzle and with some very crude
动画，我们将通过倒数晶格矢量移动它们，并显示
animation we're gonna move them by
reciprocal lattice vectors and show that
它们实际上是相同的形状，所以让我们看看它是如何工作的，我将采取
they're actually the same shape so let's
see how that works so I'm going to take
这个红色部分是第一个自己拥有的青铜色，我将获得完全相同的形状
this red section the first bronze own
I'm going to get that exact same shape
通过移动这些第一个
of the first bronze own same area same
shape exactly by moving these pieces of
第二个青铜区，所以这件作品我将互惠互利
the second bronze zone over so this
piece I'm going to move by a reciprocal
像这样的两个pi的晶格矢量，然后我将移动
lattice vector like that two pi over a
over then I'll take this piece I'll move
通过这种方式将其传递给PI，然后我将最上面的部分移至另一部分
it to PI over a over this way and I'll
take the top piece move it to part over
一个下降，另一个下降到PI，然后完全填满第一个青铜
a down and the other one to PI over a up
and it fills exactly the first bronze
自己这么好吧，我的动画技能还不是很完美，请拭目以待
own so well okay mine animation skills
are not not perfect wait to see the
另一幅甚至更糟，但是嗯，但是您得到的图像应该充满
other one it's even worse but uh but you
get the picture that is supposed to fill
第一个布里渊区刚好一次，我们没有通过
the the first Brillouin zone exactly
once and we didn't by shifting things by
实际上，两个pi并没有改变波浪，因为如果您移动
two pi over a we actually didn't change
the waves at all because if you shift by
在两个PI上，您将获得完全相同的水晶动量
two PI over a you're getting back
exactly the same crystal momentum the
通过执行相同的物理波，因此第二个青铜器有效
same physical wave by doing this
so the second bronze own is effectively
完全等同于第一个青铜器现在让我们为
exactly equivalent to the first bronze
own now let's do the same thing for the
第三个青铜将以2 pi的价格将其运送过来，以3 PI的价格将其运送过来
third bronze own will ship this over by
two pi over a this over by three PI over
好的，现在真的可以了，但是您却知道
a okay now it's really gonna get that
but but you get the idea that it's
应该能够完美契合，如果我的动画效果更好
supposed to is supposed to fit perfectly
and had I been better with my animation
技能就可以了，所以这就是
skills it would have fit perfectly okay
so that's the general general idea of a
青铜器拥有3d中关于柏林区域的一些事实，因此在3d中有格子
bronze owns there's a couple facts about
Berlin zones in 3d so in 3d the lattices
我们有兴趣让我们写下我们所需要的晶格列表
that we're interested in let's write
down a list of the lattices we're
感兴趣的主要是感兴趣的，我们有简单立方简单立方我们
interested in are mainly interested in
and we have simple cubic simple cubic we
有BCC，而我们有FCC，所以对应的倒数格子是Lisa
have BCC and we have FCC so the
corresponding reciprocal lattice is Lisa
平台很好，简单的立方晶格具有一个倒数晶格
plat is well the simple cubic lattice
has a has a reciprocal lattice which is
也简单的立方BCC晶格这是我的东西
also simple cubic
the BCC lattice this is something I
提到，我认为这是一个修正的作业问题，倒数格
mentioned and I think it's a revision
homework problem the reciprocal lattice
BCC晶格的总和为FCC，FCC晶格的倒数晶格为
sum of BCC lattice is FCC and the
reciprocal lattice of an FCC lattice is
BCC，所以第一个青铜的形状首先是BZ形状就很简单
BCC so the shape of the first bronze on
first being BZ shape is well for simple
立方晶格Figner位置单元是一个立方体，因此第一个青铜区
cubic lattice the figner site cell is a
cube so the first bronze zone for the
简单立方晶格是BCC晶格的立方，倒数晶格是
simple cubic lattice is a cube for the
BCC lattice the reciprocal lattice is
FCC，所以我们得到的东西就是FCC更大的站点单元格的形状
FCC so we get something that's the shape
of the bigger site cell for FCC which
是一个有趣的形状，它是一个截短的八面体，我给你看一张照片
was a funny shape it was a truncated
octahedron and I'll show you a picture
在一秒钟内，对于FCC晶格，倒数晶格给出BCC，所以您
in a second and for FCC lattice the
reciprocal lattice gives BCC and so you
在这里得到BCC的大型nur网站单元格我也许会说这是
get the big nur site cell for BCC here
actually I maybe said this this one is
截断的八面体现在这是截短的八面体，这是
the truncated octahedron now this one is
the truncated octahedron and this is the
让我在幻灯片上展示一下好吧，所以这是FCC的第一个铜牌
let me just show it on the slide okay so
this is the first bronze own an FCC
格子这个是树干这个是截短的八面体这个是
lattice this one's the trunk this one's
a truncated octahedron this one's a the
截短的十二面体这是12尺寸这个有14面好
truncated no dodecahedron this one is 12
size this one has 14 sides alright
无论这些是青铜拥有的形状，在这种情况下，
whatever these are the shapes of the of
the of the bronze own so in this case
FCC晶格具有互惠晶格，即BCC，这是初学者
the FCC lattice has a reciprocal lattice
which is BCC and this is the beginner
BCC晶格的Seitz单元，这是FCC的初学者Seitz单元
Seitz cell of the BCC lattice and this
is the beginner Seitz cell of the FCC
晶格也是BCC晶格的第一个青铜色，现在您会注意到
lattice which is also the first bronze
own of the BCC lattice now you'll notice
这些图片是在k空间KX KY和KZ中绘制的，您还会注意到
that these pictures are drawn in k-space
KX KY and KZ and you'll also notice that
这些图片上有一些字母，这些字母在那里
there are some letters dropped on to
these pictures these letters are there
因为人们通常在描述棕熊身上的点时
because people typically when they
describe points on in the bruins own
他们通常说我们在谈论伽玛点或x点或L
they usually say we're talking about the
gamma point or the x point or the L
点，那只是Naumann黏土的简写，您不需要
point and that's just a shorthand
Naumann clay chu that you don't need to
知道，但值得一提的是，当他们说X点时，他们拥有这些
know but it's worth knowing that they
have these when they say X point they
是指男爵区中的某个特定点，所以该点位于
mean some particular point in the barone
zone so the point in the middle of a
方形面称为X点此点此点此点
square face is called the X point this
point this point at this point the point
在一个六角形面的中间称为L点
in the middle of one of the hexagonal
faces is called the L point the point in
中心是你不需要知道的叫做伽马
the center is
it's called gamma you don't need to know
这些东西还可以，所以现在我们可以拥有这些图片
these things alright so now that we
we've can we have these pictures of the
您拥有的青铜，因为我们了解各种格子，我们可以开始考虑
bronze own for you know for our various
lattices we can start thinking about the
激发光谱电子激发光谱或声子
excitation spectra either the electronic
excitation spectra or the phonon
各种不同晶体的激发光谱，在青铜器中到处都有
excitation spectra for various different
crystals and so everywhere in the bronze
拥有的人会有所不同，例如您将拥有的缩小区域方案
own there will be different like in the
reduced zone scheme you'll have
青铜器中K的每个可能值都有不同的激励模式
different excitation modes at each
possible value of K in the in the bronze
自己做一个例子，就是这个情人节快乐的情人节
own so let's let's do an example being
this Valentine's Day happy Valentine's
所有人都可以，如果可以的话，我们要去做钻石
Day everyone is we're gonna do diamond
if alright so well we do diamond to
每年正好是今年的情人节，所以钻石
every year so just happens to be a
Valentine's Day this year so diamond do
回想一下，一个FCC晶格具有两个原子基，一个碳在零，零，零和
recall is an FCC lattice with a two atom
basis one carbon at zero zero zero and
每季度四分之一的碳，这就是
one carbon at one quarter one quarter
one quarter this is the shape of the
我们在上一张幻灯片中获得的青铜现在是第一个问题，
bronze own as we had on the previous
slide now the first question and
机会赢取巧克力每个K应该有多少个声子模式
opportunities win chocolate how many
phonon modes should there be at each K
第一个青铜器中的向量拥有多少声子模式不，不，不，不，哦，天哪
vector in the first bronze own how many
phonon modes no no no no oh my god so
印刷品中有两个原子我要自己吃一个
there's there's two atoms in the print
I'm gonna eat this one myself
好吧，今年我要增加体重，原始中没有两个原子
alright I'm gonna gain weight this year
no there's two atoms in the primitive
每个原子可以在三个可能的方向上移动，这意味着您
unit cell each atom can move in three
possible directions so that means you
有六种模式，所以让我们看看是否有它的图片，所以这是
have six modes yeah so let's see if we
have a picture of it yeah so here's
这是钻石声子光谱的图片，因此绘制方式是
here's a picture of the diamond phonon
spectrum so the way it's drawn is that
您沿着特定方向在青铜区切开
you take cuts through the bronze zone
along certain directions that you're
对这个感兴趣，例如很多，所以这里是垂直频率，然后
interested in so for example this lot so
here's the frequency vertical and then
K向量是水平的，但您在切割中给了您，所以这是切割
the K vector is horizontal but you this
given to you in a cut so this is cutting
从伽玛到X沿着1 0 0方向从伽玛到X沿着1 0 0
from gamma to X along the 1 0 0
direction gamma to X along 1 0 0
沿着这条Duyvil线的方向，然后您会知道从这里到这里是
direction along this Duyvil line here
and then you know from here to here is
伽马沿1 1 1方向从L沿该虚线到此处
gamma to L along the 1 1 1 direction
from here to here along that dotted line
这个沿1 1 0方向稍微复杂一点的x2 Gama
this one's a little more complicated
x2 Gama along the 1 1 0 direction so
实际上是从这个X穿过这个K到中间的间隙Gama
that actually goes from this X through
this K into the gap Gama in the center
下一个*区域的上方，所以有些复杂，但是现在
of the next bran zone over so that one's
a little complicated but all right now
您会注意到，如果您在此处选择一个中心点，您将
you'll notice that if you pick a point
in the center here you will count
正好有6种模式1 2 3 4 5 6如果您在这里计数，您会发现只有4种模式
exactly 6 modes 1 2 3 4 5 6 if you count
over here you'll discover there's only 4
模式为什么很好，原因是因为其中两个退化了
modes why is that well the reason is
because two of them are degenerate
您将在此处看到这两种模式，然后它们具有
you'll see these two modes coming in to
this point here and then they have the
从这里一直到这里一直有相同的能量，然后这里有两种模式
same energy all the way down from here
to here and then two modes here are
在这里退化，它们具有相同的能量或相同的频率
degenerate up here and they have the
same energy or same frequency all the
在这里，简并性的原因是因为您正在寻找
way over here and the reason for the
degeneracy is because you're looking
沿着特定的对称方向，在该方向上横向振动
along a particular symmetric direction
where vibrations transverse in this
方向和该方向上的横向振动看起来相同
direction and vibrations the transverse
in that direction look identical
而沿着这个方向是非常不对称的方向，所以所有方向
whereas along this direction it's a very
unsymmetric direction so all directions
振动实际上具有不同的能量，您可以看到
of vibration actually have different
energies you can see a couple
有趣的是，在此图中，伽玛点为K等于0，
interesting things in this in this
figure the gamma point is K equals 0 you
可以看到下降到2 K的声模线性等于0，这些是
can see the acoustic modes coming down
to 2 K equals 0 linearly and these are
此处的光学模式处于高频状态，这些模式之一是
the optical modes up here at at high
frequency and one of these modes is
纵向两个是横向的现在我们可以问相同的问题
longitudinal two of them are transverse
now we can ask the same questions about
电子激发光谱，当您计算电子
an electronic excitation spectrum and
when you calculate an electronic
在这种激发光谱中，您必须确定类型绑定近似值
excitation spectrum in this a type
binding approximation you have to decide
您将要在每个原子上考虑多少轨道，因此
how many orbitals you're going to
consider on each on each atom so for
在上图中的示例中，我们考虑了每个晶胞两个轨道，因此
example in that picture up there we
considered two orbitals per unit cell so
考虑到典型的碳计算类型，您不想保留所有
given that a typical type of calculation
for carbon you don't want to keep all
轨道延伸到无穷大，所以通常您只需保持轨道
the orbitals out to infinity so
generally you just keep the orbitals
您对通常感兴趣的是什么轨道感兴趣
you're interested in what one is usually
interested in is the orbitals where
虽然有1到1
there's some sort of interesting action
going on that though the 1 the 1
轨道有一个核心轨道，它们只是完全没有被填充
orbitals there was a core orbitals
they're just completely filled nothing
有趣的是，那里的三个3s 3p轨道等等
interesting going on there the orbitals
that are three 3s 3p and so forth those
完全是空的，完全没有意思
are just completely empty totally
uninteresting the ones that are
有趣的是有些是部分填充，部分是空白
interesting are the ones that are sort
of partially filled partially empty
这些是2s和3 2p轨道，因此考虑到3s
those are the 2s and the 3 2p orbitals
so given that we're considering the 3s
和三个2p轨道有多少激发
and the
three 2p orbitals how many excitation
模式特征值应该在青铜器的每个K点处找到一次
modes eigenvalues should be find at each
K point in the bronz own one more chance
我们正在考虑每个原子有四个轨道，你说的答案是八，是的
we're considering four orbitals per atom
what was the answer eight you say yeah
好吧，哦，差不多他们到了八点，是的，所以有两个轨道
okay so Oh almost they got there all
right eight yeah so there's two orbitals
如果您算出您需要做的是，您需要算出
per if you count what you you need to do
is you need to count the total number of
每个基本晶胞的轨道，这将为您提供
orbitals per primitive unit cell and
that will give you the total number of
每个K向量的激励模式现在，此图为激励
excitation modes per per K vector now
this diagram this is an excitation
这些东西是钻石的电子激发光谱
spectrum an electronic excitation
spectrum of diamond these things are
由于其明显的原因，通常被称为意大利面条图，因为它看起来
frequently known as spaghetti diagrams
for obvious reasons because it looks
像一碗复杂的意大利面，你说不通
like some sort of complicated bowl of
spaghetti that you can't make any sense
的，但实际上是相当简单的
of but but it's actually it's it's
fairly simple
嗯，不是那么复杂，您正在查看削减的内容
well not that not that complicated
what's again you're looking at cuts
通过青铜器本身，所以这是L和伽玛点之间的一条线
through the bronze own so this is a line
between the L and gamma point along this
槽虚线，这是一条从伽玛到X的直线，沿着该虚线，然后是X
slot dotted line this is a line from
gamma to X along this dotted line then X
到KK到伽玛，所以基本上只是削减铜牌
to KK to gamma so it's basically just
taking cuts to the bronze own and at
每个K点有八种模式一二三四五五六七八
each K point there are eight modes one
two three four five six seven eight and
有些方向看起来好像只有六个，让我们来看一下
some in some directions it looks like
there's only six let's see for example
这个方向一二三四有五六，因为其中两个已经成为
this direction one two three four five
six because two of them have become
退化在这里看到这两个一起走了哦，这两个来不挂
degenerate here see these two came
together oh no hang on these two came
一起在这里只做一个，因为实际上有两种模式
together here to make only one that's
because there's actually two modes with
同样的能量，所以您现在必须对此稍加注意
the same energy so you have to be a
little bit careful about that for now
碳的化合价为4，这意味着每个碳都贡献四个电子
carbon has a valence of four which means
each carbon donates four electrons and
这意味着我们已经捐赠了每个原始晶胞两个碳
that means with two carbons per
primitive unit cell we have donated
总共八个电子，所以您同时用两个自旋填充了底部四个带，因此
eight electrons total so you fill the
bottom four bands with both spins so the
当有间隙时，底部的四个带被填充
bottom four bands are filled when
there's a gap and you have the upper
四个乐队，事实上，正如我们稍后将在几个讲座中讨论的那样，
four bands and in fact as we'll discuss
in a couple lectures later on that means
我们所拥有的是我们有一个非常好的绝缘子填充带，而不是一个很大的间隙
what we have is we have a really good
insulator filled bands than a big gap
然后是一堆空乐队，这也使钻石变得漂亮，
and then a bunch of empty bands it's
also what makes diamond nice and
透明的，使钻石足够美丽
transparent so it makes diamond
beautiful appropriately enough for
情人节好吧，让我们从这里继续
Valentine's Day alright so let's move on
from here
认为今天的钻石足够了，所以其中之一是
think that's enough of diamond for today
so one of the things that's fairly
这个故事很重要，这是因为我们始终具有紧密的结合光谱
important about this is this story is it
with our tight binding spectra we always
的原则是，如果您将K乘以K加G，您就会准确地得到
have the principle that if you take K to
some K plus G you get back exactly the
同一波，您对振动也有相同的原理
same wave and you have the same
principle for vibrations as well now you
可能会问这个原理，是否当您将K倒数倒数
might ask whether this principle that if
when you shift K by a reciprocal lattice
向量是否对紧绑定逼近特别有用
vector whether that is actually special
to the tight binding approximation we
使用或是否实际上是一般性声明让我们提醒自己
use or whether this is actually a
general statement let's remind ourselves
为什么我们在紧密绑定模型的退出时找到了这个
why it is that we found this for an exit
for for tight binding model basically
紧密束缚波函数这与我的语言略有不同
the tight binding wave function this is
in a slightly different language than I
之前写过，但是您可以将它写为IK点R倍
wrote it before but you can you can
write it as e to the I K dot R times
坐在晶格点R上的电子，这是我们常称的东西
electron sitting on lattice point R this
is this is we used to call this thing
Phi，我们给了这个，嗯，不，我觉得差不多，我想区别是
Phi and we gave this uh no I think it's
more or less I guess the difference is
现在我们在三个维度而不是一个维度中进行操作，这就是为什么
now we're doing in three dimensions
rather than one dimension that's why it
看起来有点不同，但这基本上是紧束缚波函数
looks a little different but this is
basically a tight binding wave function
我们之前写下的东西在取k 2k的情况下显然是不变的
that we wrote down before and this thing
is obviously invariant under taking k 2k
加g是因为当您将g按ET i移位k时，e会传给i gr
plus g because e to the i okay oops
e to the i gr when you shift k by g ET i
g点r等于1，因为g在倒数晶格中，而R在正晶格中
g dot r equals one because g is in the
reciprocal lattice and R's in the direct
晶格，因此，如果k偏移了g，则此处不会更改此因子，您
lattice so if k gets shifted by g it
doesn't change this factor here and you
回到同一波，所以你可能会问这是否仅仅是一个属性
get back the same wave so but you might
ask whether this is just a property of a
紧密绑定模型，或者如果这实际上是普遍的
tight binding model or if this is
actually something that's general and
这实际上是一个非常重要的问题，也是后来出现的一个问题
this is actually a really important
question and it's a question that came
在发现缩短方程后很短的时间内
up very shortly after the discovery of
the shortening equation shorting a
1926年在1928年发现他的方程式，人们已经担心
discovered his equation in 1926 in 1928
that people were already worried about
这个问题，并由Felix Bloch著名地解决了，
this issue and it was resolved very
famously by block Felix Bloch and what's
被称为布洛赫定理布洛赫定理好吧，这经常
known as Bloch's theorem Bloch's theorem
all right okay which is frequently
被称为所有材料科学的基础，这是基础
referred to as the underpinning of all
of material science it's an underpinning
在你所有的物理学中，这是非常重要的
of all of
your physics it's an extremely important
直到我们谈论一些
principle which may not seem so
important until we talk about some of
它的含义，但让我先陈述定理，然后我们将证明
its implications but let me state the
theorem first then we'll prove the
定理，然后我们将讨论其中的一些含义，因此该陈述是
theorem then we'll talk about some of
the implications so the statement is an
电子在周期电势中在周期电势中周期V
electron in a periodic potential in
periodic potential potential periodic V
的RI猜测周期均值R的V等于VR加V等于R的大写R
of R I guess periodic means V of R
equals V R plus V a capital R with
作为晶格矢量的大写R具有本征态形式的本征态
capital R being a lattice vector has
eigenstates of the form as I ghen states
形式很多符号在这里第二叹息R的子K等于e
of the form a lot of symbols here for a
second sighs sub K of R equals e to the
IK点R乘以u的u上标alpha sub sub K
I K dot R times u superscript alpha sub
K of our where where u is periodic so
如果您将其从R移到U，则等于R的U加R和Cays，
it's the same if you shift it from you U
of R equals U of R plus R and Cays and
可以在第一个古铜色中选择k可以在第一个古铜色中选择
k's can be chosen in the first bronze
own can be chosen in first bronze own
换句话说，K是晶体动量K是晶体波矢量晶体波
in other words K is crystal momentum K
is crystal wave vector crystal wave
向量
vector
这种形式被称为这种叹气形式
this form is known as this form of sigh
叹气被称为修正平面波被称为修正平面
of sigh is known as a modified plane
wave is known as as a modified plane
挥动一个修改过的平面波修改一个应该相当平的平面波
wave a modified plane wave modified a
plane wave that that should be fairly
很明显，这是到IKr的平面波e，并乘以
obvious it's a plane wave e to the IKr
and is modified by being multiplied by a
周期函数，你就是平面波指数的修改
periodic function you that's the
modification of the plane wave the index
alpha alpha是乐队索引，乐队索引旨在描述您所知道的
alpha alpha is the band index and the
band index is meant to describe you know
如果您在这里谈论这一点，您将获得不同的波动函数，或者
you get a different wave function if
you're talking about this point here or
这一点在相同的K向量处，您可以知道相同的K向量
this point here at the same K vector at
the you know same K vector you can have
不止一个本征态，所以能量本征能量是
more than one eigenstate so the energies
eigenenergies are e superscript alpha of
K所以e1和e2取决于我们在讨论哪个频段
K so e1 and e2 depending on which which
band we're talking about which which
最低的能量级别是下一个下一个最小值中的下一个最小值，因此
energy level the lowest are the next
lowest of the next next lowest and so
好的，这是我们在这里所做的一大堆声明，但是
forth okay so this is a pretty big bunch
of statements we've made here but it's
相当重要，因为它可以告诉您有关
fairly important because it tells you
about the general structure of
本征态处于周期性势，所以让我们首先证明这个定理，然后
eigenstates in a periodic potential so
let's first prove this theorem and then
我们将讨论为什么这个定理如此重要，为什么它如此重要
we'll talk about why this theorem is so
important and why it underlies so much
材料科学和半导体物理学等
of material science and semiconductor
physics and so forth
所以首先好吧，这是一个准证明，它实际上相当严格，但是
so first okay so this is sort of a quasi
proof it's actually fairly rigorous but
好吧，不会早点填写细节，但是准证明像这样
well will sooner not fill in the details
but the quasi proof goes like like this
首先我们考虑一下我们的哈密顿量
first we'll consider our Hamiltonian
which is H naught just the free electron
哈密​​顿量加上我们的势v是周期性的，所以V是周期性的
Hamiltonian plus our potential v which
is periodic so V is periodic
如果我们丢掉定期
and H naught is the usual P squared over
2m now if we threw away the periodic
我们会知道本征态的潜力，所以这些仅仅是平波本征态
potential we would know the eigenstate
so those are just plain wave eigenstates
打波，呃，他不好，好吧，我们不是，你知道k只是h的平方
playing waves uh he not ok ok we're anot
you know of k is just the h bar squared
k超过2m的平方，我们通常到目前为止到目前为止，我们知道我们有飞机
k squared over 2m we usually have so so
far so good we know we have the plane
波浪，那么我们现在必须添加周期性电势
waves then we have to add the periodic
potential now what can the periodic
周期性的势能将您从一些K散布到一些K Prime
potential do the periodic potential can
scatter you from some K to some K Prime
通过这种形式的矩阵元素，现在我们对这种矩阵元素了解很多
via a matrix element of this form now we
know a lot about matrix elements of this
从我们从散射理论中学到的东西形成这个矩阵
form from what we learned in scattering
theory this thing here this matrix
周期电势V从平面波k到平面波K prime的元素
element from a plane wave k to a plane
wave K prime via a periodic potential V
是u的傅立叶变换在K减去时求出的傅立叶变换
is the Fourier transform Fourier
transform of u are evaluated at K minus
K素数，如果K减K素数K减K素数是，则其为0
K Prime and that is the following it is
0 if K minus K prime K minus K prime is
不是倒数晶格向量不等于G，如果
not a reciprocal lattice vector is not
equal to G and we'll call it V sub G if
K减去K素数等于G，我将其称为K素数减去K等于G，并且
K minus K prime equals G I'm gonna call
it K prime minus K equals G that and
这只是老挝的缓解条件，但您可以从波矢k散射到
this is just Lao ease condition but you
can scatter from a wave vector k to a
仅当K和K素数之差为a时，波矢量K素数
wave vector K prime only if the
difference between K and K prime is a
倒易晶格矢量，当我们研究x射线的散射时我们学到了这一点
reciprocal lattice vector we learned
this when we study scattering of x-rays
和中子等等，这几乎可以证明我们
and neutrons and so forth
so this gets us almost to the proof so
我们几乎可以在这里得出结论，为什么这里要点是
we can almost conclude the result here
why well the point here is that the
具有散射势的哈密顿量为块对角线无双点
Hamiltonian with the scattering
potential is block diagonal no pun
对角线块
intended
block diagonal block with a K diagonal
我的意思是，如果k和k，您可以从k分散到ak素数
what I mean by this is that you can
scatter from k to a k prime if k and k
素数被g隔开，然后从k素数可以分散到另一种情况
prime are separated by g and then from k
prime you can scatter to another case
如果双引号被一个G隔开，则可以分散到另一个K素
double prime if those are separated by a
G and you can scatter to another K Prime
依此类推，依此类推，等等，但是您永远无法改变水晶
and so forth and so on and so forth but
you can never change the crystal
动量，通过周期的散射可以得到的所有K
momentum all of the K's that you can get
to by scattering by the via the periodic
通过互逆的晶格矢量使它们彼此不同
potential all of them different from
each other by reciprocal lattice vectors
所以哈密尔顿分手了，如果你愿意的话，你进入这些领域
so the Hamiltonian breaks up and if you
into these sectors if you like and so
波动函数的形式必须为psy K，且必须为G的总和。
the wave function must be of the form
psy K must be of the form sum over G of
一些系数我们称它们为mg加K乘以e到I k加G的点
some coefficients let's call them a mg
plus K times e to the I k plus G dotted
用r然后为什么它必须是这种形式，所以从e开始
with r then why should it have to be of
this form well you start with some e to
IKr，然后将其混合成汉密尔顿量
the IKr and then you mix into that the
Hamiltonian mixes into that different
平面波，其波矢量K相差互相关矢量G和
plane waves whose wave vector K differs
by a reciprocal reliance vector G and
您可以根据需要将它们混合使用，它们都会得到一些系数
you can mix in as many of those as you
want and they all get some coefficients
但是到了最后，波动函数必须仅是事物的诗篇
a but at the end of the day the wave
function must be a psalm only of things
具有相同的晶体动量k加上一些倒易的晶格矢量g
that have the same crystal momentum k
plus some reciprocal lattice vector g
没有办法比较耳部潜力可以改变您的
there's no way that compare otic
potential can take you can change your
水晶气势是重要的认识
crystal momentum that's the important
realization good yeah
好的，好吧，所以从这里我们已经完成了很多，因为你可以
happy good all right so from here we're
pretty much done because you can just
将e分解为IK点R，然后在G Plus K中有超过G的部分
factor out the e to the I K dot R and
then you have some over G of a G Plus K
e到i gr，这是r的周期函数uu
e to the i gr and this piece here is the
is the periodic function u u of r which
而且您可以说这件事一定是周期性的，因为如果您将e转到i
and you can tell this thing must be
periodic because if you take e to the i
用r加r点缀的gg通过直接空间晶格矢量移动它
g g dotted with r plus r move it by a
direct space lattice vector this thing
与e到点R相同，所以这是周期性的
is the same as e to the i okay dot R so
this thing is periodic
如所声称的还可以，我们还可以检查如果您服用K而您会发生什么
as claimed okay furthermore we can also
check what happens if you take K and you
将其移动一个互逆的晶格矢量G，所以让我们实际采用这种形式
shift it by a reciprocal lattice vector
G so let's let's actually take this form
的K到这里，让我们将K加G的正弦值，实际上我已经使用过
of K up here and let's shift K by G sine
of K plus G actually I've already used
字母G，所以我们称其为G素数，将其移位K-K加G素数
the letter G so let's call this G Prime
shift it by K - K plus G Prime
因此，我们将其写为G加sub G加K加G素数e等于IK加G的总和
so we'll write it as sum over G a sub G
Plus K plus G prime e to the I K plus G
素数加G，但总和超过虚拟索引，因此我们可以定义一个虚拟
prime plus G but this sum is over a
dummy index so we can define a dummy
索引，它称为G旋转等于GG旋转
index
it's called G twiddle equals G G twiddle
向量等于G加G的素数向量，然后用那个代替
vector equals G Plus G prime vector and
then if you substitute that in that
成为G旋转向量的总和，G旋转向量加K e至i k r k +
becomes sum over G twiddle vector a G
twiddle vector plus K e to the i ke r k+
g旋转向量点r，它与我们开始时的表达式完全相同
g twiddle vector dot r which is exactly
the same expression that we started with
到那里，所以如果您将k倒移晶格向量g，
up up there so if you shift k by a
reciprocal lattice vector g you get back
完全相同的波动函数，这就是我们试图在
exactly the same wave function which was
what we were trying to answer in the
首先是特殊的是，当您按倒数晶格向量移动k时
first place is it's special that when
you shift k by reciprocal lattice vector
你会得到完全相同的波动函数，这对紧
you get back exactly the same wave
function is that special to the tight
绑定模型不是它是较短方程和周期的属性
binding model it's not it's a property
of the shorter equation and periodic
可能还可以，所以这个定理的含义是
potential okay all right so the
implications of this theorem which is
被视为如此重要是一种暗示，一种激发一切
viewed as so important is one
implications one an excitation all
可以描述所有的激励z'
excitations can be described all
excitation z' can be described be
在一个BZ拥有的一枚青铜中描述，因为
described
in one bronze owned in one BZ because
每当您走出青铜所有者的大门时，您都可以相互交换
whenever you go outside of the bronze
owner you can just shift by a reciprocal
晶格矢量回到第一个，然后回到那个*区域
lattice vector to get back into the
first it back into that bran zone so
这是一个重要的声明第二个重要的声明可能更多
that's an important statement second
important statement may be more
重要的是周期性电势不会改变
important is that periodic potential a
periodic potential does not change does
不分散晶体动量，这是我之前提到的
not scatter crystal momentum and this is
something that I mentioned before when
我们讨论了一个紧结合模型，该模型保持了晶体动量。
we discuss a tight binding model that
the crystal momentum is conserved the
水晶动量始终保持不变，因为我们拥有
crystal momentum is always conserved in
the fact that that we have this very
强大的周期性潜力不会破坏这就是如此的原因
strong periodic potential doesn't ruin
that this is the reason this is so
重要的是请记住，当我们研究Sommerfeld模型
important remember we had this puzzle
when we study the Sommerfeld model that
你有电子的平均自由程，这是巨大的李长
you have this mean free path of
electrons which is enormous Li long
数百个原子或数千个原子长，我们无法理解
hundreds of atoms or thousands of atoms
long and we couldn't understand it
因为有一个大原子核，原子可以击中几乎每一个你不知道的原子
because there's a big nucleus that the
atom can hit every you know few
埃可以从数吨的核子中飞散而来
angstroms it could scatter off of tons
and tons of nuclei the point here is
你没有纯粹的平面波，你拥有的是修改过的平面
that the it you don't have pure plane
waves what you have is modified plane
波具有这些平面波乘以周期函数，但是一旦修改
waves you have these plane waves times a
periodic function but once you modify
将该平面波乘以该周期函数，则它是完美的
the plane wave by multiplying it by this
periodic function then it's perfectly
好的平面波可以完全穿过系统而不会发生散射
good plane wave to go all the way across
the system without scattering at all so
如果你带一个电子，你会把它放在一个小波包中
if you take a you know an electron you
put in a little wave packet of this
修改过的平面波，只要它在整个系统中传播，
modified plane wave it would travel
clear across the system as long as it
不会碰到任何杂质或类似我们的讨厌的东西，但它可以
doesn't hit any impurities or our nasty
things like that but it could go all the
整个系统之间完全没有分散，因此这种解决方案解决了我们
way across the system without scattering
at all so this sort of resolves our our
电子为什么能在没有电子的情况下传播那么远的最初问题
initial issue of why it is that
electrons can travel so far without
没有分散好吗，这个结果是从哪里来的
without scattering okay and where did
this this result come from it's
重要的是要意识到这个重要结果确实来自毛伊岛的状况
important to realize that this important
result really came from maui's condition
这是因为周期性的电势仅以倒数的方式散射
it came from the fact that a periodic
potential only scatters u by reciprocal
波向量没问题，所以这对我们不起作用的一件事是
wave vectors all right so the one thing
that this doesn't do for us is
无法解决它并不能帮助我们解决较短的问题
does not manage to it does not manage to
help us actually solve the shorter
方程式，因此解决缩短方程式的难度仍然很大，我们已经
equation so solving solving shortening
your equation is still hard and we've
已经讨论了一种实现方法，一种实现方法是类型绑定和按类型
already discussed one way to do it one
way to do it is type binding and by type
绑定我们真正在做的是从原子轨道开始
binding what we're really doing is we
start with start with atomic orbitals
与原子轨道，并允许周跳允许周跳，但那
with atomic orbitals and allow week
hopping allow week hopping but that
听起来可能有点不通用，因为跳跃可能很强烈
might sound a little non-generic because
maybe the hopping is strong be from one
放在另一个地方，因此非常感谢您从一个角度思考它
place to another so it's useful to thank
you very useful to think about it from a
非常互补的观点，而不是从紧密的约束开始
very complimentary viewpoint where
instead of starting with a tight binding
我们从平面波开始的模型从平面波开始平面波和
model we start with plane waves start
with with plane waves plane waves and
加上R的弱周期性电位V，所以完全相反
add weak periodic potential V of R so
it's entirely the opposite way of
看一下这种方法的两种方法是已知的
looking at things
this approach approach to two is known
因为几乎是自由电子模型，几乎是自由电子模型，
as the nearly free electron model nearly
free electron model and it's a very
一个有用的模型，可用于理解许多半导体和能带的物理性质
useful model for understanding a lot of
the physics of semiconductors and band
固体中的结构，让我们开始吧，我们大概开始吧
structure in solids so let's let's go
about that let's start it we probably
想今天完成它，所以我们如何开始
want to finish it today
but the so how do we do this we start
我们的H零在K上是平面波而没有周期性势，所以更容易
with our H zero on K are plane waves
without the periodic potential so easier
好吧，在K上我们很容易Rho是通常的H条平方K平方超过2m，这是
okay on K we're easy Rho is the usual H
bar squared K squared over 2m it's a
一个好的开始，然后让我们假设V弱假设V弱
good place to start and then let's
assume V is weak assume weak V
好的，那么当您对一个物体的微弱干扰时该怎么办
all right so what do you do when you
have a weak perturbation to an
汉密尔顿算术，您使用的是您可能最后了解的微扰理论
hamiltonian well you use perturbation
theory which you presumably learned last
年，所以您还记得微扰理论中能量发生了什么变化
year so you remember what happens to the
energies in perturbation theory so it's
不以一阶扰动理论一阶扰动能量
not with first order perturbation theory
first order order pert the energy this
大概熟悉本征态K的波能
probably look familiar
the energy of the wave the eigenstate K
是没有干扰加上一阶的光秃秃的能量
is the bare energy without the
perturbation plus the first order
摄动理论项，即KVK和此处的矩阵元素
perturbation theory term which is K V K
and this matrix element here
好吧，我将其滚动到了面板的顶部，也许我没有，也许我没有
well I scrolled it off the top of the
board No maybe I didn't maybe I did I
认为我确实将其定义为V sub 0，因为K减去K为0且该V sub 0
think I did we defined it as V sub 0
because K minus K is 0 and this V sub 0
对于所有K，对于所有K都是相同的，所以这仅给出了一个整体常数
is the same same for all K for all K so
this just gives an overall constant
本征态的能量转移，因此本征态需要转移
energy shift of the the eigenstates so
they the eigenstates need to get shifted
能量上升或能量下降，这是零
up in energy or they get shifted down in
energy this is sort of the zeroth
这种势的傅立叶模式，无论在其顶部添加什么恒定势
Fourier mode of this potentials whatever
constant potential is added on top of
任何波动的势能都会在空间中发生变化，因此零傅立叶
any fluctuating potentials things that
change in space so the zeroth Fourier
势的模式只是将K的整体能量上下移动
mode of the of the potential just shifts
up and down the overall energy of K does
这个表达式看起来像您刚刚熟悉的一阶微扰理论
this expression look familiar first
order perturbation theory you just take
专家API很好，所以这并不有趣
the expert API ok
good so this is not interesting in as a
事实上，人们经常放弃v-0，因为他们太无趣了
matter of fact people frequently dropped
v-0 because it's so uninteresting they
只是摆脱它，我会尽力保留它，但也许我会误以为忘记它
just get rid of it I'll try to keep it
but maybe I'll forget it by mistake at
一点，所以二阶更有趣，所以它是二阶
some point so second-order is more
interesting so it's second-order you
拥有EK等于EK并不是裸露的东西加上v-0是一阶
have EK equals EK not that's the bare
piece plus v-0 that's the first-order
件，然后您有二阶件，它是K素数之和不等于
piece and then you have the second-order
piece which is sum of K prime not equal
到K，则我们有K个素数VK乘以B个子N的平方N减去e个素数
to K then we have K prime V K squared
over B sub K naught minus e K prime not
设置正确的顺序是的，从二阶微扰中看起来很熟悉
set the right order yeah does that look
familiar from second-order perturbation
好的理论现在好了，我们对此有什么了解
Theory good all right
now what do we know about this second
同样，我们有楼上矩阵元素的老挝缓解条件，
well again we have Lao ease condition
for the upstairs matrix element that in
该矩阵元素为非零的顺序
order for that matrix element to be
nonzero
您必须有K个素数减去KI必须等于一个倒数晶格向量G，所以
you must have K prime minus K I must
equal a reciprocal lattice vector G so
该术语在这里可以重写为互易的晶格矢量G的总和
this term here can be re-written as sum
over G of reciprocal lattice vectors G
V sub G的平方，其中G是K素数减去K / e sub K等于n减去e sub K
of V sub G squared where G is K prime
minus K / e sub K naught minus e sub K
加G看起来不太满意，还可以，所以这是我们的表情
plus G not good look happy with that
somewhat okay so this is our expression
对于我们开始的平面波能量的二阶位移，
for the second-order shift in energy of
the plane waves that we started with but
我们必须对看起来像这样的表达式和
we have to be a little bit careful about
expressions that look like this and the
我们必须谨慎的原因是因为您可能会遇到两种情况
reason we have to be careful is because
you might have a situation where the two
分母中的两个术语彼此相等，在这种情况下，
terms in the denominator are either
equal to each other in which case you
下楼为零或彼此非常接近，在这种情况下
get zero downstairs or very close to
each other in which case you get
楼下很小的东西，无论哪种情况，二阶项都会
something very small downstairs and in
either case the second-order term would
爆炸，在这种情况下，您会有分歧，这意味着
blow up in which case you have a
divergence and that means the
二阶微扰理论是不正确的，因此您必须小心
second-order perturbation theory is not
correct so you must be careful be
小心当esup k这恰好是e sub K大约不等于e sub
careful when esup k this just right it's
e sub K not approximately equal to e sub
k加G现在什么时候发生
k plus G naught now when does that
happen
e sub K实际上正好与K平方成正比，因此
well e sub K is actually just
proportional to K squared so that will
当绝对k等于绝对好加g时发生
happen when absolute k equals absolute
okay plus g well where's that you
记得在这里某处，这是存在的条件
remember somewhere here
there it is it's the condition for being
当您在青铜自己的边界上时，在青铜自己的边界上
on a bronze own boundary when you're on
bronze own boundary et sub K and E sub K
+ G实际上是相同的让我们为它画一幅画
+ G are actually the same let's actually
draw a picture of that so what we have
是的，这是我们的Barre光谱还可以，而II，Barre光谱只是一个
is we have a this is our Barre spectrum
okay and II the barre spectrum is just a
抛物线，所以这是e sub K是H bar平方而不是K平方超过2m，这是
parabola so this is e sub K is H bar
squared not K squared over 2m and here's
此处a的PI减去a的PI，并且这两个能量分开
PI over a here's minus PI over a and the
energy of these two these are separated
通过一个互易的晶格矢量，两个PI在a上，它们的能量相同，因此
by a reciprocal lattice vector two PI
over a and their energy is identical so
这将使我们在二阶微扰理论上出现分歧
this would give us a divergence in
second order perturbation theory
类似地，如果我们在a上减去负2 PI，在a上减去2 PI，则这些被a隔开
similarly if we go to minus 2 PI over a
and 2 PI over a these are separated by a
a上的倒数晶格矢量4 PI和它们的能量相同，所以它们
reciprocal lattice vector 4 PI over a
and their energies are identical so they
将使您在二阶微扰理论上有分歧，所以这个地方
will give you a divergence in second
order perturbation Theory so the place
二阶微扰理论失败的地方恰好是您在青铜上
where second order perturbation Theory
fails is exactly when you're on a bronze
自己的边界，所以我们需要做的是
own boundary so what we're going to need
to do is we are going to need to
可能下次必须做这个，但是我们要做什么来解决这个问题
probably gonna have to do this next time
but what we're going to do to fix this
通过使用退化扰动理论解决问题
problem fix a problem by using using
degenerate perturbation Theory
退化它是摄动理论第三理论
degenerate
it's a perturbation theory third theory
希望你已经学到了一些东西，所以我们不会
which hopefully you've learned something
about already so we're not gonna have
是今天开始的时间，所以我要真正抓住机会
time to launch into that today so I'm
going to actually take the opportunity
插入一条信息，或者可能插入两条信息
to insert one piece of information or
maybe two piece of information about
我答应过你，我们会谈谈的
scattering that I promised you we would
talk about sometime and that is
分散的东西，所以也许我会把它放在这里
scattering off of so maybe I'll put that
over here scattering off of
X射线和中子散射X射线和中子散射这是不同的
x-rays and neutron scattering x-ray and
neutron scattering this is a different
受试者刚刚插入了这最后五分钟，从
subject just inserted in this last five
minutes neutron scattering from from
液体液体和无定形固体形态固体，因此在液体和
liquids liquids and amorphous solids
morphus solids so in liquids and
无定形固体我们没有周期性结构我们没有周期性
amorphous solids we do not have periodic
structures we do not have periodic
原子的排列，但是尽管如此，您仍然可以从中获得很多信息
arrangement of atoms but nonetheless you
get a lot of information out of the
中子X射线散射，如果您想回到我们做费米金像时
neutron x-ray scattering if you think
way back to when we did Fermi's Golden
规则，即散射幅度仍然是物体的傅立叶变换
Rule that the scattering amplitude is
still the Fourier transform of the
电位的周期性，但不是傅立叶变换的周期性
periodic of the potential but it's not a
periodic potential its Fourier transform
超过非周期性的潜力，但这是否意味着其中没有任何信息
over the non periodic potential but does
that mean there's no information in it
不，其中仍然有信息，只是您没有得到尖锐的峰
no there's still information in it it's
just that you don't get sharp Peaks
现在你得到的是在这里，所以这是液体上的X射线散射
anymore what you get is here there it is
so this is x-ray scattering on liquid
铝，它被加热到高温，所以它是液体
aluminium it's heated up to some high
temperature so it's so it's a liquid
有散射角或倒数向量的函数
there's a function of the scattering
angle or the reciprocal wave vector
那就是沿着这个轴的波向量，散射的幅度是
that's the the wave vector along this
axis the amplitude of scattering is has
峰和峰大致代表了原子之间的距离
Peaks and the peaks represent roughly
the distance between between atoms it's
1在原子之间的距离上以相同的方式表示峰
1 over the distance between atoms the
same way the peaks represent the
现在晶胞变成晶体时的周期性是
periodicity of the unit cell when it
becomes crystalline now what happens is
当您冷却液体时，它变得越来越结晶，
as you cool down a liquid and it gets
more and more crystalline that becomes
越来越多的本地秩序，这些山峰变得越来越尖锐，
more and more local order and these
Peaks get sharper and sharper and
最终变得更加清晰，当事物真正结晶时，它们就变成了三角洲
sharper and finally when the thing
actually crystallizes they become Delta
函数以我们期望的方式达到晶体的峰值，但是如果是
function Peaks the way we expected them
to for for a crystal but if it's a
液体，您可以将液体视为本地
liquid it's sort of you can sort of
think of a liquid as locally being like
固体，您知道每个原子都有几个邻居，但是如果您看起来
a solid you know each atom has a couple
neighbors but if you sort of look
更远的地方它不再有序了
farther away it's not ordered anymore it
sort of loses its order but if you sort
只是在某个小区域的外观，您可能已经知道它是有组织的
of look just in some small region it
probably has you know it's organized
在一个很小的区域内，因此您会在散射中得到这些宽峰
over a small region so you get these
sort of broad peaks in in the scattering
频谱好吧，我想也许我今天不会尝试涵盖任何其他问题，
spectrum okay I think maybe I won't try
to cover any further issues today and
我们将在星期三再次开始，我认为周末愉快
we'll start again on
Wednesday I think have a good weekend
[掌声]
[Applause]